Finding Aid for Louis H. Fead papers, 1900-1948
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Louis H. Fead papers 1900-1948 1918-1942
Fead, Louis H., 1877-1943.
851414 Aa 2
Associate justice of the Michigan Supreme Court; correspondence, speeches and other materials relating to Michigan politics, Republican Party affairs, and his judicial career.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
6 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Marion McPherson Fead Pratt (Donor no. 3471 ) and came to the library in 1966.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Louis H. Fead was born on May 2, 1877 in Michigan's Upper Peninsula. After graduating from Olivet College, he moved to Detroit where he worked in the law offices of Bacon & Palmer while also attending the Detroit College of Law. In 1898, he enrolled in the University of Michigan Law School receiving his Bachelor of Laws degree in 1900. After graduation, he returned to the Upper Peninsula opening a practice in Newberry. He soon became Prosecuting Attorney for Luce County serving from 1901 to 1913.
In 1912, he was elected to the Circuit Court of the eleventh district, an office he held until 1928 when Governor Fred W. Green appointed him to the Michigan Supreme Court. He presided as chief justice from 1928 until 1937, when he was defeated in his bid for re-election. He died February 4, 1943.
The Louis Fead collection includes correspondence, scrapbooks, biographical information and other materials relating to his political and judicial career. Some of the files relate to the view from Michigan of the proposed reorganization of the US Supreme Court in 1937. There are also materials concerning the Newberry State Bank of which Fead was an officer. Also of interest are those materials relating to his service with the American Red Cross in France during World War I.
Subjects:
Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1928.; Elections--Michigan--1930.; Elections--Michigan--1934.; Elections--Michigan--1936.; Elections--Michigan--1938.; Elections--Michigan--1940.; Elections--Michigan--1942.; Fead, Louis H., 1877-1943.; Freemasonry--Michigan.; Luce County (Mich.); McPherson, Hugh Alexander, 1864-1965.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Newberry (Mich.); Newberry State Bank (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States. Supreme Court.; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Red Cross.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fraternal organizations.; Freemasonry.; Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Alexander Joseph), 1873-1953.; Judges--Michigan.; Michigan. Supreme Court--ca. 1929.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Law. Class of 1900.; World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Bohn, Frank Probasco, 1866-1944.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Butzel, Henry M. (Henry Magnus), 1871-1963; Fretz, William G., 1869-; Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Perry, Henry Ernest, 1866-; Rushton, Herbert J., 1877-1947.; Sayles, Alexander L., 1887-; Taylor, Sam C.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  - Biographical information and other personal material (Box 1)
  - Personal clippings (Box 1)
  - World War I material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1912-1928, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of congratulation upon appointment to the Supreme Court February-March 1928 (Box 1)
  - 1929-1930, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - 1931-September 1934, 20 folders (Box 2)
  - October 1934-April 1938, 16 folders (Box 3)
  - May 1938-December 1942, 14 folders (Box 4)
- Other materials
  - Letters of condolence and memorial resolutions 1943 [sample] (Box 4)
  - Memorial resolutions (Box 4)
  - Obituaries and funeral miscellanea (Box 4)
  - Correspondence relating to Fead's estate, personal affairs, etc. 1943-1948 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Family letters
    - 1938 (Box 4)
    - 1939 (Box 4)
    - 1940 (Box 4)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Addresses, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Stockholder's reports, business and investment reports, announcements, proxies, etc., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Insurance papers (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous bills and receipts undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous documents, pamphlets, etc. (Box 6)
  - Mementoes, pamphlets, clippings, etc. relating to World War I 1915-1918 (Box 6)
  - Red Cross papers undated (Box 6)
  - Thesis entitled, "May Husband and Wife Carry on Business as Partners?" 1900 (Box 6)
  - Clippings undated (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook on the University of Michigan 1913-1915 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook kept by Mrs. Hugh A. McPherson, Louis H. Fead's mother-in-law, concerning McPherson and Fead families circa 1915-1947, photocopy (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
Selective Index to Corespondents
Bohn, Frank Probasco, 1866-1944.
1927-1942.
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973.
1929-1942.
Butzel, Henry Magnus, 1871-
1928-1938.
Fretz, William G., 1869-
1928-1942.
Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.
1936-1942.
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860
1927-1940 (scattered).
Perry, Henry Ernest, 1866-
1931-1940 (scattered)
Rushton, Herber J., 1877-1947.
1933-1940.
Sayles, Alexander L., 1887-
1929-1942.
Taylor, Sam C.
1931-1972.
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
1929-1940.